Kirk Long

1440 N Locust Grove Rd BLDG 34 APT B Meridian, ID, 83642 +1 (208) 297-0396 kirklong@u.boisestate.edu https://linkedin.com/in/kirkalan

Research Interests

I am excited about employing advances in modern computing to analyze large data-sets and to simulate interesting systems numerically. I am broadly fascinated with the evolution of our universe and its systems, with a particular interest in dense stellar objects and the processes that form them (including the various flavors of neutron stars). I have enjoyed combining these passions in my research thus far, which has focused on identifying accreting pulsars in x-ray binaries.

Education

08/2017 - 05/2020

Boise State University, Honors College

Bachelors of Science in Physics, Astrophysics emphasis

Minors in Music and Applied Mathematics

Cumulative GPA (including transfer credits): 3.859/4.0

Physics GPA: **3.946/4.0**

Best GRE Scores: 166 (89th %) Quantitative — 164 (94th %) Verbal

5.5 (98th %) Analytical Writing

08/2015 - 05/2017

Idaho State University

Attended prior to transferring to Boise State, originally intended to major in math and music here.

Research Experience

04/2019 - Identifying accreting x-ray binaries, Boise State University

Mentored by Dr. Daryl Macomb, code sample available at: https://github.com/kirklong

- Analyzed archival data taken with both the CHANDRA and XMM-Newton orbital X-ray observatories, with data reduced via HEAsoft and SAS.
- Used FFT analysis to find periods of pulsar sources, then compared periods of co-located sources in data from both instruments over time to detect changes that could be driven by accretion.
- Used techniques like bootstrapping to generate statistical significances of potential detections from background data.
- Built folded light curves of potential new pulsar sources and accreting pairs.

Teaching Experience

08/2018 - Physics Lab Instructor, Boise State University Department of Physics

Responsible for teaching, grading, and managing class of students ($\sim 25/\text{class}$). Evaluations available for all courses upon request. Courses taught include:

- PHYS 111 (General Physics I, Fa 2018)
- PHYS 105 (Introductory Stars and Cosmology, Sp 2019)
- PHYS 101 (Survey of Physics, Fa 2019)
- PHYS 204 (Introductory Astronomy, Fa 2019)
- PHYS 211 (General Physics I for Scientists and Engineers, Sp 2020)

08/2018 - Physics Tutor, Boise State University Department of Physics

1/2 students selected by Department to host drop-in tutoring lab (lead tutor 2019-2020). Taught mostly lower-division coursework but occasionally helped with more advanced topics. Average attendance per session: ~ 5 students.

01/2019 - Volunteer, Idaho Department of Corrections

Inspired by Bryan Stevenson's Just Mercy to start program for inmates to learn STEM skills.

Taught introductory programming (Python) class 1 hour/week with partial summer hiatus.

- Created curriculum based on programming classes taken and research experiences.
- Built Jupyter Notebook "labs" for inmates to follow.

01/2020 - TA/Grader, Boise State University Department of Physics

Responsible for grading homework assignments for upper division Classical Mechanics course.

Outreach

06/2015 -

Telescope Operator, Bruneau Sand Dunes State Park Observatory Former volunteer of >300 hours before being hired in March of 2017.

Responsible for maintenance and operation of various large telescopes and related equipment.

- Used telescopes to show visitors celestial objects with accompanying explanations of both objects and equipment.
- Experience with various makes of telescopes with apertures up to 0.64 m (25").

Tasked with creating and giving \sim 45 minute public talks/presentations.

- Topics curated from latest research and most popular phenomena in astronomy, distilled into form digestable by those without any previous background knowledge.
- Average crowd size: ~ 150 . Total visitors during employment: > 20,000.

01/2019 -

Volunteer, Idaho Department of Corrections

Work detailed here in addition to volunteer teaching detailed above.

Brought outreach events each week to local prisons to stimulate interest/continued attendance in prison education programs (supplied by BSU Physics Department). Occasionally helped with GED lessons when applicable to physics.

Originally volunteered at just men's facility but have recently (11/2019) started expansion into women's as well.

Press: Featured on Boise State University website (08/2019) and on local news channel KIVI (11/2019).

05/2016 -

STEM Lead, Treasure Valley Family YMCA

In charge of writing STEM curricula for summer camps and after school programs for all 4 local YMCA branches, including coding and physics programs.

- Engaged and inspired $\sim 1,000$ program attendees during employment.
- No child turned away: $\sim 1/5$ of participants received financial assistance.
- Responsible for procuring/maintaining thousands of dollars worth of equipment.
- Trained \sim 50 employees on STEM materials and how to effectively teach topics.

Collected and analyzed budget and participant data throughout summer months.

08/2016 - 08/2018

Intern, StarTalk

Wrote blog posts on convoluted and/or newsworthy astronomy/physics topics.

- Posts disseminated to online audience of >500,000.
- Writing can be found by searching for my name on the *StarTalk* website: https://www.startalkradio.net/?s=kirk+long
- Occasionally still write guest posts, but main affilliation ended 2018 due to uneasingness regarding accusations against Neil.

12/2019 -

@ThreeBodyBot, Twitter #scicomm

Built automated Twitter account that posts random three body simulations $\sim 1/\text{day}$. Source code available at https://github.com/kirklong/ThreeBodyBot.

Scholarships and Awards

2015 - 2017	Presidential Scholarship	\$10,000
2017 - 2018	Dean's Transfer Scholarship	\$3,000
2018 - 2019	Whitlock Math and Science Award	\$800
2018 - 2019	BSU Foundation Honors Award	\$1,500
2018 - 2019	Physics Department Scholarship	\$1,000
2019 - 2020	Honcik Physics Scholarship	\$3,000
2019 - 2020	George Campbell Memorial Award	\$2,800
2016 -	Dean's List	

Skills (rated basic – expert)

• Programming Languages:

Advanced: Python, Julia
Competent: Matlab, Bash
Basic: Perl, Fortran, JavaScript

• Software:

- Expert: Microsoft Office Suite

- Advanced: Jupyter Lab/Notebook, Anaconda, terminal/command line

- Beginner: HEASOFT, SAS, LaTeX

- Basic: MESA, Git

• Operating Systems:

- Advanced: Windows 10

- Competent: Mac OSX, Linux (Mint)

Posters and Publications

Macomb, D. & Long, K. (2020). Identifying accreting x-ray binaries. In preparation.

Long, K. (2018). To the Moon and Back – Simulating the Trajectory of a Multi-Stage Rocket Similar to Saturn V in an Apollo 8 Mission Analogue.

Poster available on Github (https://github.com/kirklong/Posters), presented on:

• 02/2019: Research Computing Days, Boise State University

• 12/2018: Won best class poster from PHYS 325 (Scientific Computing)

Barkley, K., Belnap, K., Keller, M., Larson, J., **Long, K.**, McCarthy, K., Myers, M., & Withers, J. (2017). *Idaho State University (a campus history)*. Charleston, SC: Arcadia. ISBN: 1467125512.

Relevant Coursework

Physics & Math: Classical Mechanics (Taylor), Electrostatics and Electrodynamics (Griffiths),

Introductory Quantum Mechanics (Krane), Introductory Relativity/Particle Physics,

Optics (Pedrotti), Thermal and Statistical Physics (Schroeder), Astrophysics,

Engineering Physics (Knight), Cosmology (Sp 20), Circuits (Sp 20),

Linear Algebra, Single/Multivariable Calculus (Stewart),

Ordinary Differential Equations (Boyce/DiPrima)

Computing: Scientific Computing (Newman), Computational Mathematics,

Parallel Scientific Computing (Sp 20), Introductory Computer Science

Extracurricular Activities

I enjoy spending time outdoors (particularly hiking and skiing), tinkering with amateur science projects (I've built cloud chambers, homemade rockets and fireworks, DIY telescopes, a brick kiln for metallurgical experimentation, and more), and making and teaching music (I've partly financed my studies thus far working at a local studio). I particularly enjoy learning and performing classical piano works—the latest addition to my repertoire is Gershwin's *Rhapsody in Blue* and my favorite piece is Rachmaninoff's *Prelude in G Minor*.